Guide to the John McComb Architectural Drawings Collection 1766-1829 PR 40
New-York Historical Society
John McComb architectural drawings collection
1766-1829
New-York Historical Society
McComb, John, 1763-1853
PR 40
95 Linear feet (circa 730 drawings)
The John McComb Architectural Drawing Collection spans the period from ca. 1766-1829 and primarily contains architectural drawings of New York City Hall and other McComb projects.
Access to Collection
Collection is open for research; access requires at least 24 hours advance notice.
Scope and Contents Note
The John McComb Architectural Drawing Collection spans the period from ca. 1766-1829 and primarily contains architectural drawings. Most drawings are untitled and undated. The collection is notable in part because almost all of the buildings it depicts have disappeared (one notable exception is the New York City Hall). Drawings are one of the only sources of architectural history from that time period; this is one of the largest body of drawings from the Federal period. The collection contains 642 architectural drawings, 24 engineering drawings, 13 maps, and 60 engravings.
The New York City Hall drawings are filed by a separate numbering system (CHxxx) and described in that sequence in a logbook compiled by McComb descendant Edmund S. Wilde. Wilde also inscribed his own notes directly on some drawings and erased some of Mangin's signatures. City Hall Drawings date from [1802]-[1811] with the majority being from 1803. The series features 135 elevations, sections, plans and detail drawings for New York City Hall, McComb's foremost work. 50 of these also have drawings on their verso, for a total of 185 drawings. As City Hall has been renovated and added on to several times since its inception, these plans are an important record of the original building. In addition, the difference between the competition drawing plans and the final plans shows how the building changed while in progress. Many of these drawings were conserved in 1986.
The remaining drawings were numbered from 1-263 at some point between 1898 and 1967. In 1967 the numbering was resumed from 300-456. There are nine drawings that lack numbers, including most of the American Tract Society. Drawings span the time from John McComb Sr.'s day to the last days of McComb Jr.'s architectural career. Drawings include engineering drawings, decorative designs, studies and school problems, sketches of buildings designed by other people, and hand-drawn copies of real estate maps. The series contains drawings attributed to McComb's relatives (including 5 attributed to John McComb Sr.), partners, to Jacob Lawrence; and 38 engravings by Giambattista Piranesi and others. Few of the collection's drawings are fully identified commissions.
Among the over 100 church designs, 34 have been associated with 7 specific New York churches, including St. John's Episcopal Chapel, North Dutch Church, Bleecker Street Presbyterian Church, Ceder Street Presbyterian Church, Murray Street Church, and Wall St. Presbyterian Church. The 40 engineering drawings feature McComb's lighthouses at Cape Henry, Virginia, and Montauk Point and Eaton's Neck, New York; as well as sewers, machinery, and fortifications. The few commercial buildings include a bakery, sugar refinery, and City Hotel.
Another 60 drawings depict townhouses, including those built for Rufus King, Rev. Benjamin Moore, and John B. Coles. Plans for larger houses include drawings for a stone mansion in Westchester for Dominick Lynch, a wealthy Irishman. Several designs show double houses, an architectural phenomenon with no surviving built examples.
The 50 drawings for public buildings portray Alexander Hall, the American Tract Society, Castle Clinton, Government House, the Park Theatre (designed by Joseph Francois Mangin), Queen's Building at Rutgers, Rickett's Equestrian Amphiteatre, Vanderlyn's Cyclorama Rotunda, and the Washington Benevolent Society headquarters. An insane asylum, a hospital, and other public structures are shown. A drawing of an engine house is possibly by John McComb Sr.
Notes on the collections, the numbering system, and provenance appear in: Gilchrist, Agnes Addison, "Notes for a Catalogue of the John McComb (1763-1853) Collection of Architectural Drawings in the New-York Historical Society," Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians 28 (Oct. 1969).
Biographical/Historical Note
John McComb (Oct. 17, 1763-May 25, 1853) was the principal architect in New York City between 1800 and his retirement in the 1820s. He also became one of the most important architects of the Federal period in the United States. Most of McComb's designs show a heavy reliance on English forms, especially that of Robert Adam. His style has been described as late colonial-neoclassical. McComb's father, John McComb Sr. (1734-1811) was also an architect, builder, and surveyor in colonial and post-Revolutionary New York City. McComb began his career as a bricklayer. He first made a reputation as a churchbuilder in the 1760s. After the Revolutionary War McComb Sr. helped organize the General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen. McComb Sr. worked as a city surveyor for a number of years and was commissioned to repair the Bridewell Asylum, among other New York buildings damaged in the War.
John McComb Jr., the eldest of three children, was born in New York City, and became his father's assistant in 1783. His independent work began around 1790, when he was commissioned to build the Government House, an intended home for the new United States president. The building was not finished before the federal government moved to Pennsylvania, but New York governors used the house until 1797 when the state capitol was moved to Albany. Another major activity of McComb Jr. during the 1790s was building lighthouses. McComb's lighthouses at Montauk Point (1795) and Eaton's Neck (1797-8), New York and at Cape Henry, Virginia (1791-2) are all still standing.
McComb's early work also included townhouses, double houses, and more opulent country houses. He built a stately town house for John B. Coles, lawyer and politician, at 1 State Street (1797-9) and another for U.S. Senator Rufus King (1795). McComb designed Rev. Benjamin Moore's house on 9th Avenue and 20th Street (1794) and The Grange, Alexander Hamilton's country estate in Harlem (1801-2). McComb's unorthodox interest in unusual room shapes is evident in his many untitled residential drawings.
In 1800 the New York City Common Council held a design competition for a new City Hall. The joint entry by Joseph Francois Mangin (who purportedly drew most of the original designs) and John McComb was awarded the top prize of $350 in 1802. Subsequently, McComb was named as chief architect and superintendent of construction. The design combines McComb's Federal style with a French Neoclassicism that was undoubtedly Mangin's contribution. Construction took a decade; the exterior construction was finished in 1811, interiors were completed the following year. While supervising City Hall construction, McComb was concurrently involved in many other projects. He designed the building of the Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen on Park Place (1802-3), the New York Free School House (1808), and the Hubert Street Fort (1808). He designed plans for the Washington Benevolent Society headquarters, Washington Hall (1809-14), and the Queen's Building at Rutgers University in New Jersey (1808-11).
McComb followed in his father's footsteps by designing many churches. He and his younger brother Isaac McComb (1776-1810) designed St. John's Episcopal Chapel (1803-7). McComb worked alone on the Cedar Street Presbyterian Church (1807-8) and the Murray Street Presbyterian Church (1811-12).
He also worked on another city building, the Fort at the Battery (known as Castle Clinton since the War of 1812.) Although the entire design was once thought to have been McComb's idea, it is now considered the work of Colonel John Williams. McComb may actually have only designed the entranceway. He did serve as the building contractor between 1807-1811.
Once City Hall was completed, McComb continued to work as an architect and builder, although his most productive years were drawing to a close. McComb was made a Street Commissioner and a City Surveyor of New York in 1813, and served in that capacity until 1821. Under this aegis, McComb planned streets, sewers, canals, and piers. His interest in canals and sea travel made him an early advocate of the Erie Canal, and he was remembered in his obituary (Illustrated News, June 11, 1853) as a supporter of Fulton's steamboat career.
McComb designed and built Alexander Hall at Princeton Theological Seminary (1815-17) and the American Bible Society Building on Nassau Street (1822-23). In 1817 he was considered as a possible architect for the United States Capitol building. John McComb Jr. was awarded many honors during his career. He was named an Academician of the American Academy of Fine Arts in 1816, and served on the board of that organization from 1817-28. McComb was a member of the General Society of the General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen from 1787, and served as its president in 1818. He was also a member of the Masonic Order.
McComb journeyed to Philadelphia in May 1822, where he visited and sketched the works of other architects, especially William Strickland, Robert Mills, and John Haviland. Philadelphia architecture was then beginning to be heavily Greek influenced; moving away from the English influence of the colonial style. As is evidenced in a sketchbook from that trip, McComb paid special attention to churches, mainly to facades and interior plans of sanctuaries. The few buildings he designed after 1822 show evidence of his interest in the changing styles. The Bleecker Street Presbyterian Church (1823-26), one of McComb's last works before his retirement, is notable for its Doric columns, elements not found on earlier McComb churches.
In 1822 McComb renovated and added a new steeple to the Brick Presbyterian Church, which had been designed by his father. He then designed the Youle shot tower (1822-23) at East River and 53rd Street, the first such structure in New York, and the building for the American Tract Society (1825-26).
After his retirement, McComb devoted his time to his family life. John McComb, Jr. married Elizabeth Glean in 1792. They had three children, Mary ([1795]-1848), John III (1798-1858), and Matilda. Elizabeth died in 1817; McComb married widow Rebecca Rockwell in 1821. John McComb III became an attorney, although he did some drafts work for his father at a young age. Mary was an accomplished artist who painted many of her father's structures.
McComb was civic minded and served public and private institutions throughout the city in many capacities. In many cases these were organizations whose buildings he had designed or built. He was a trustee of the Brick Presbyterian Church from 1816 to 1825, and a deacon from 1827 until his death. In 1923 he became a lifetime member of the American Bible Society. In 1818 he was named a Governor of New York Hospital and served in that capacity until at least 1832. He was a director of the Mechanics Bank in 1820. After leaving the world of architecture, John McComb entered into some mercantile ventures in the interest of his property investments. In 1829-30 he was president of the La Fayette Insurance Company.
The last twenty years of McComb's life were spent almost totally out of the public eye. He died in New York at age 90. He is buried at Greenwood Cemetery in Brooklyn.
Sources: Gilchrist, Agnes Addison, "John McComb, Sr. and Jr., in New York, 1784-1799," Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians 31 (Mar. 1972.)
O'Gorman, James F. "A New York Architect Visits Philadelphia in 1822," The Pennsylvania Magazine of History & Bibliography, 117 (July 1993).
Related Archival Materials Note
Certificates of John McComb and Mrs. McComb (the second) are in the Certificate File (PR 014.) Photographs of the three lighthouses can be seen in the Lighthouse Photograph and Print Collection (PR 038.) A photograph of the Coles Residence (now demolished) can be found in the Tiemann Collection (PR 129). The Manuscript Department at the New-York Historical Society holds the McComb family papers, including account books, correspondence, and other material. Several maps drawn by John McComb are held by the New-York Historical Society Library. The New-York Historical Society Museum holds John McComb's drawing board and other artifacts including Mary McComb's painting of the Montauk Point lighthouse.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was given by Daniel Parish, Jr. in 1898, 1905, and 1909. The remaining drawings were given by McComb's descendents: Edmund S. Wilde, 1902; Mrs. Helen A. Collingwood, 1930; and Miss Abbie Collingwood Miller, 1949. A few drawings were purchased by the Society in 1923.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Architects; Architecture -- United States -- 18th century -- Designs and plans.; Architecture, American -- 19th century -- Designs and plans.; Buildings -- New Jersey.; Buildings -- New York (State); Buildings -- Virginia.; Church buildings -- New York (State); Commercial buildings -- United States -- Designs and plans.; Country homes.; Dwellings.; Floor plans.; Governors -- Dwellings -- United States.; Historic buildings -- United States -- Designs and plans.; Lighthouses -- Virginia.; Public buildings -- United States -- Design and plans.; Row houses.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Cadastral maps.; Detail drawings; Elevations (orthographic projections).; Engravings (prints); Building plans.; Sketches.; Technical drawings.; Watercolors (paintings); McComb, John, 1763-1853; McComb, John, 1734-1811; Mangin, Joseph Fr. (Joseph François), 1764-1818; New Theatre (Organization: New York, N.Y.); New York City Hall (New York, N.Y.); Princeton Theological Seminary; Rickett's Equestrian Amphitheatre; Vanderlyn's Cyclorama Rotunda; Washington Benevolent Society
- "Catalogue of Books on Architecture. [?] Belonging to John M.Comb Jun.r": UL-UR, 1808 (Box McComb Box 22)
- Unidentified project, pencil, LC: "Coat of Arms or Masonic Badge" (Box McComb Box 16, Item 315)
- Unidentified project, Profile of moldings: attributed (Box McComb Box 18, Item 369 1/2 verso)
- Unidentified project, "ORDINANCES AND RULES CONTROLLING THE USE OF CROTON WATER.", 1851; January 15 (Box McComb Box 17, Item 339)
- Unidentified project, 1901 (Box McComb Box 22, Item 461)
- Unidentified project,, ink, MC: "A View of the Monument of the Dutchiss of Northumberland" (Box McComb Box 16, Item 314)
- Unidentified project, ink, UL: "one Revolutions" (Box McComb Box 20, Item 431 verso)
- Unidentified project, [Two sepulchral monuments, 1 wall and 1 floor] (Box McComb Box 16, Item 316)
- Unidentified project, ink, MC-MR: "Fronts of churches and skitches Doors - etc" (Box McComb Box 16, Item 322)
- Unidentified project, Rusticated doorway with paneled soffit: attributed (Box McComb Box 18, Item 369 1/2)
- Unidentified project [possibly old Queens Building at Rutgers University] (Box McComb box 6, Item 114)
- 4 story public bldg. Facades, unidentified (Box McComb Box 21, Item 457)
- Academy of [Fine] Arts see inscription, 1817, July (Box McComb Box 14, Item 232)
- Academy of Fine Arts ink, LC: "Plan disigned for an academy of The Fine Arts-" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 196)
- Academy of Fine Arts [attributed] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 199a recto)
- Academy of Fine Arts [attributed] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 197)
- Acton Bridge Mr. Jos Howlands Estimate for rebuilding Acton Bridge. Ink UR (Box McComb box 2, Item 29)
- Alms House pencil, LL-LR: "Sketch shewing how the South Front of the Alms House may be altered" (Box McComb Oversize Drawer, Item 412)
- Alms House ink, ML-MR: "Sketch of the first floor of the Alms House" (Box McComb Box 21, Item 443)
- Alms House, attributed ink, UC: "This Plan - covers an Area of 5376 Feet" (Box McComb Oversize Drawer, Item 413)
- Alms House, attributed ink, UC: "The part of the Plan marked A will accomodate about 60 pauper patients and may erected separately. the other part to be added, as ci (Box McComb Oversize Drawer, Item 413 verso)
- American Tract Society "Plan of the Cellar Story-": __, LC
- American Tract Society "Third Story": ___, LC
- American Tract Society "This Design to be Executed": ___, LR
- American Tract Society "Plan of First Floor": __, LL-LC
- American Tract Society "Fourth Story": ___, LC
- American Tract Society "2d Floor": ___, LL-LC
- American Tract Society "The Design for the Front on Nassau Street having been altered - this front must be made to corrispond -": ___, LL-LR
- American Tract Society "Section of South Westerly end-": ___, LC-LR
- American Tract Society, attributed ink, LL-LR: "Elevation on Nassau Street" (Box McComb Box 14, Item 234)
- Anchorage House, attrib. ink, LC: "SECOND STORY.", [1840] (Box McComb Box 21, Item 450)
- Anchorage House, attrib. Main facade: attrib., [1840] (Box McComb Box 21, Item 446)
- Anchorage House, attrib. ink, LC: "PARLOR STORY.", [1840] (Box McComb Box 21, Item 449)
- Anchorage House, attrib. Side facade: attrib., [1840] (Box McComb Box 21, Item 447)
- Anchorage House, attrib. ink, LC: "BASEMENT", [1840] (Box McComb Box 21, Item 448)
- Arch details, attributed (Box McComb Box 20, Item 419)
- Arch profiles (Box McComb box 1, Item 024b)
- Architectural details, attrib. (Box McComb Box 17, Item 343 verso)
- Arsenal Yard, Wall and Gateway ink, MC: "Plan & Elevation of Wall & Gate Way for Arsenal Yard On State & White Hall Streets" (Box McComb Box 9, Item 435)
- Assembly Hall/Theatre, attributed ink, MC: "hall with a large sky light" (Box McComb Box 19, Item 398)
- Bake shop Ink, LC-LR: "Plan for the ovens of the N. York Bakery Jn.MComb - arch s" (Box McComb Box 5, Item 92)
- Bake shop, pencil, LL (Box McComb Box 5, Item 93)
- Balusters (Box McComb Box 17, Item 337)
- Bank ink, LL-LR: "By this plan it is proposed to remove the 2d floor the Banking to be 2 stories high-" (Box McComb Box 15, Item 267)
- Banner - General Society of Mechanics & Tradesmen (Box McComb Box 17, Item 345)
- Black Friars Bridge ink, UL-UR: "Longitudinal Section of Caisson used for Laying the Piers of Black Friars Bridge London 1766" (Box McComb Box 20, Item 415)
- Black Friars Bridge ink, UC: "Black Friars Bridge", [1766] (Box McComb Box 20, Item 416)
- Black Friars Bridge A Rib of the Centering for the Middle Arch of Blackfrairs Bridge. Ink UL to UR (Box McComb box 2, Item 28)
- [Bleeker Street Presbyterian Church] Bleecker Street Presbyterian Church: [attributed] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 180)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church, [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 193)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church ink, UL-UR: "Sketch of Ceiling for Bleecker Street Church-", [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 190a recto)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church, 1825; January (Box McComb Box 11, Item 185a recto)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church, [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 187a recto)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church graphite, ML-MR: "First View designed for Bleecker Street Church-", [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 189)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church ink, LL-LR: "Bleecker Street Church", [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 192)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church, 1825; January (Box McComb Box 11, Item 185b verso)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church, [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 187b verso)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church graphite, LL-LR: "Plan for Bleecker St. Church", [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 184)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church Letter from John Aspinwall: [attributed], 182[?]; 29 Octo. (Box McComb Box 11, Item 191)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church [attributed] pencil, LR: "The church to be 61 feet by 84 feet in length", [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 188)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church [attributed] NA, [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 186a recto)
- Bleecker St. Presbyterian Church [attributed], [1823-1825] (Box McComb Box 11, Item 186b verso)
- Boissas Hydraulic Ingine Examination of Mr Boissas Hydraulic Ingine which he conceiv'd would produce perpetual motion. Ink UL (Box McComb box 2, Item 34)
- Bow Church Steeple (Box McComb box 1, Item 024a)
- Bracket designs (4) attrib. (Box McComb Box 18, Item 353)
- Brick Presbyterian Church ink, MC-MR: "Sketch showing an idea of altering the Steeple of Brick, Presbyterian church - 25 feet was cut down in the Year 1822-" (Box McComb Box 16, Item 320)
- Brick Presbyterian Church ink, UL-UR: "Brick Presby. Church" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 181)
- Brick Presbyterian Church (Beekman St. by J. McComb Sr.) graphite, MC: "82 Pews in Gallery", 1822; Dec. 14 (Box McComb Box 11, Item 182b verso)
- Brick Presbyterian Church (Beekman St. by J. McComb Sr.) ink, ML-MR: "Plan of Brick Presbyterian Church Beekman St. Built 1767" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 183)
- Brick Presbyterian Church (Beekman St. by J. McComb Sr.) ink, LL-LR: "Plan of the Brick Presbyterian Church in Beekman St. as altered in the Year 1822-", 1822, December 14 (Box McComb Box 11, Item 182a recto)
- Brick Presbyterian Church (Beekman St. by J. McComb Sr.) ink, UL-UR: "Brick Church 1821" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 182a(suppl.))
- Brick Presbyterian Church [attributed] Steeple [attributed] (Box McComb Box 9, Item 146)
- Brick Presbyterian Church, attrib. Steeple (Box McComb Box 16, Item 313)
- Bridewell ink, LC-LM: "Dimentions of the Bridewell" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 198)
- Bridewell [attributed] ink, LL-LC: "Plan of the second floor" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 195)
- Bridewell [attributed] ink, LC: "Plan of First Floor" (Box McComb Box 11, Item 194)
- Bridewell alteration Sketch for Alteration of the Bridewell (?) [attrib T.F.H.], [1792] (Box McComb box 1, Item 11)
- Bridge Wooden bridge supported by stone piers: attributed, 1814; February 24 (Box McComb Box 12, Item 206)
- Building, unidentified (Box McComb box 4, Item 73)
- Bulkhead for a Quay ink, ML-MC: "A method of Constructing a Bulkhead for a Quay", 1817; April 10 (Box McComb Box 17, Item 342)
- C. Hoxie's Threshing Machine C. Hoxie's Threshing Machine (Box McComb box 1, Item 8)
- Canal ink, UC: "Canal Street" (Box McComb Box 12, Item 207)
- Canal graphite, ML-MR: "Section of the Canal at West Street" (Box McComb Box 12, Item 204)
- Canal Bridge pencil, LC: "Section of the Canal at the Intersection of Chapel and Laurens St" (Box McComb Box 12, Item 209)
- Canal Bridge, attributed (Box McComb Box 12, Item 208)
- Castle Clinton Ink, LC-LR: "Sketch for the Sea Wall at the battery", 1807-1811, [attrib.] (Box McComb Box 9, Item 155)
- Castle Clinton Ink, LC: "Gate Way for Battery", 1807-1811 [attrib.] (Box McComb Box 9, Item 153)
- Castle Clinton, 1807-1811 [attrib.] (Box McComb Box 9, Item 152)
- Castle Clinton Ink, LC: "Plan of the Lower Battery", 1807-1811, [attrib.] (Box McComb Box 9, Item 151)
- Castle Clinton Entryway, attrib. (Box McComb Box 22, Item 460)
- Cedar St. Presbyterian Church Ink, LL-LR: "Plan of the Cedar Street Church", 1807 (Box McComb Box 8, Item 128)
- Cedar St. Presbyterian Church, attributed graphite, LL-LR: [Cedar St. Presbyterian Church, by John McComb 1807] (Box McComb Box 8, Item 130)
- Cedar St. Presbyterian Church, attributed graphite, LL-LR: [Window detail of church resembling Cedar St. Presbyterian] (Box McComb Box 8, Item 127)
- Cedar St. Presbyterian Church, attributed S.s., graphite, LL-LR: [Resemblance to Cedar St. Presbyterian Church], 1807 (Box McComb Box 8, Item 129)